<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 14-12-22">
  <num>14-12-22</num>
  <heading>Resolution Number TMBC 14-12-22 of the Duly Elected and Certified Governing Body of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2022-12-29</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/14-12-22.pdf">Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 14-12-22</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2022-12-22</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, hereinafter referred to as the Tribe, is an unincorporated Band acting under a revised Constitution and By-Laws approved by the Secretary of the Interior on June 16<sup>th</sup>, 1959 and amendments thereto approved; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Article IX (a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-Laws empowers the Tribal Council with the authority to represent the Band and to negotiate with Federal, State, and Local Governments and with private persons; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Article IX (a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and Bylaws requires a 30-day comment period prior to the adoption of any ordinances or amendments to the Tribal Code, whether proposed by resolution or otherwise. Adoption must occur through a roll call vote of the Tribal Council at a publicly held meeting; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe adopted the Law Enforcement Act of 2017 (Chapter 50.06) by Resolution No. TMBC 448-08-17, to provide for public safety through proactive and responsive law enforcement services; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe is amending Title 50, Chapter 50.06 Section 50.0615 to add the attached proposed amendments to Section 50.0615 of the Law Enforcement Act of 2017 and amend the title of Chapter 50.06 to DIVISION OF LAW ENFORCEMENT-THE LAW ENFORCEMENT ACT OF 2017; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe, by Resolution No. TMBC 1970-11-12, is approved a comment period for proposed amendments to the Law Enforcement Act of 2017 by adding to Title 50, Chapter 50.06 Section 50.0615 the attached proposed amendments and amend the title of Chapter 50.06 to DIVISION OF LAW ENFORCEMENT-THE LAW ENFORCEMENT ACT OF 2017 to provide for public safety through proactive and responsive law enforcement services; and to educate and serve the public and no comments were received; now</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribe is approving the amendments to Title 50 as presented and will codify the Tribal Code accordingly.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, Tribal Secretary of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, do hereby certify that the Tribal Council is composed of <em><strong>nine (9) members</strong></em> of whom <em><strong>eight (8)</strong></em> constituting a quorum were present at a meeting duly called, convened and held on the <em><strong>22<sup>nd</sup> day of December, 2022</strong></em> that the foregoing resolution was adopted by an affirmative vote of <em><strong>seven (7) in favor</strong></em> - Representative Ron Trottier, Sr., Jon Jon Keplin, Lynn Gourneau, Craig Lunday, Kenneth Malaterre, Elmer Davis, Jr. and Chad Counts, one (1) absent- Reps. Blaine "Slugger" Davis; none (0) opposed; none (0) absent; with the Tribal Chairman not voting.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Jolean A. Morin, Tribal Secretary</text>
    <text>( ) SIGNED INTO LAW/Dated this ___ day of __________, 2022</text>
    <text>( ) VETOED/Dated this ___ day of __________, 2022</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Jamie Azure, Tribal Chairman</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
