<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 1913-10-22">
  <num>1913-10-22</num>
  <heading>Resolution Number TMBC1913-10-22 of the Duly Elected and Certified Governing Body of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2022-10-19</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/1913-10-22.pdf">Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 1913-10-22</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2022-10-06</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, hereinafter referred to as the Tribe, is an unincorporated Band acting under a revised Constitution and By-Laws approved by the Secretary of the Interior on June 16<sup>th</sup>, 1959 and amendments thereto approved; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Article IX (a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-Laws empowers the Tribal Council with the authority to represent the Band and to negotiate with Federal, State, and Local Governments and with private persons; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Article IX (a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and Bylaws requires a 30-day comment period prior to the adoption of any ordinances or amendments to the Tribal Code, whether proposed by resolution or otherwise. Adoption must occur through a roll call vote of the Tribal Council at a publicly held meeting; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Title 52, the Tribal Health Emergencies Code was out for 30-day public comment with no issues on the proposed amendment to Title 52; now</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribe is approving proposed amendments to Title 52 of the Tribal Health Emergencies Code.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, Tribal Secretary of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, do hereby certify that the Tribal Council is composed of <em><strong>nine (9) members</strong></em> of whom <em><strong>nine (9)</strong></em> constituting a quorum were present at a meeting duly called, convened and held on the <em><strong>6<sup>th</sup> day of October, 2022</strong></em> that the foregoing resolution was adopted by an affirmative vote of <em><strong>eight (8) in favor</strong></em> - Representatives Chad Counts, Ron Trottier, Sr., Kenneth Malaterre, Elmer Davis, Jr., Lynn Gourneau, Blaine "Slugger" Davis, Jon Jon Keplin, Craig Lunday; none (0) opposed; with the Chairman not voting.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Jolean A. Morin, Tribal Secretary</text>
    <text>( ) SIGNED INTO LAW/Dated this ___ day of __________, 2022</text>
    <text>( ) VETOED/Dated this ___ day of __________, 2022</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Jamie Azure, Tribal Chairman</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
