<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 218-03-23" codify:doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <num>218-03-23</num>
  <heading>Resolution Number TMBC218-03-23 of the Duly Elected and Certified Governing Body of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-03-23</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/218-03-23.pdf">Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res.No. 218-03-23</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-03-23</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, hereinafter referred to as the Tribe, is an unincorporated Band acting under a revised <cite doc="Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-laws">Constitution and By-Laws</cite> approved by the Secretary of the Interior on June 16th, 1959 and amendments thereto approved; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-laws" path="IX|1">Article IX(a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-Laws</cite> empowers the Tribal Council with the authority to represent the Band and to negotiate with Federal, State, and Local Governments and with private persons; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-laws" path="IX|1">Article IX(a) Section 1 of the Turtle Mountain Constitution and By-Laws</cite> requires a 30-day comment period prior to the adoption of any ordinances or amendments to the Tribal Code, whether proposed by resolution or otherwise. Adoption must occur through a roll call vote of the Tribal Council at a publicly held meeting; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe is proposing revisions to <cite doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code" path="5">Title 5</cite>, Children's Code to provide for waiver into adult court for children who commit class 4 and 5 offenses and age out prior to federal review; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe, by Resolution No. TMBC110-02-23, approved a 30 day public comment period for proposed revisions to <cite doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code" path="5">Title 5</cite>, Children's Code, and no comments were made; now</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribe is approving revisions to the Tribal code, <cite doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code" path="5">Title 5</cite>, Children's Code, as published in the comment period notice; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Code will be codified accordingly, to insert amendments to <cite doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code" path="5">Title 5</cite>.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned Tribal Secretary of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, do hereby certify that the Tribal Council is composed of <strong><em>nine (9)</em></strong> members of whom <strong><em>seven (7)</em></strong> constituting a quorum were present at a meeting duly called, convened and held on the <strong><em>23<sup>rd</sup> day of March, 2023</em></strong> that the foregoing resolution was adopted by an affirmative vote of <strong><em>six (6) in favor</em></strong> - Representatives Craig Lunday, Ron Trottier, Sr., Elmer Davis Jr., Blaine "Slugger" Davis, Kenneth Malaterre and Chad Counts; two (2) absent- Representatives Lynn Gourneau and Jon Jon Keplin; none (0) opposed; with the Chairman not voting.</text>
    <text>__________________________</text>
    <text>Jolean A. Morin, Tribal Secretary</text>
    <text>(  ) SIGNED INTO LAW/Dated this ___ day of ___________, 20__</text>
    <text>(  ) VETOED/Dated this ____ day of ______________, 20__</text>
    <text>__________________________</text>
    <text>Jamie Azure, Tribal Chairman</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:replace path="|5.02.130" codified:doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code" codified:path="|5.02.130">
    <section>
      <num>5.02.130</num>
      <heading>Transfer to Adult Court</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Court may, at its discretion, allow prosecution of any delinquent juvenile fifteen (15) years or older in accordance with the laws of the Turtle Mountain Jurisdiction governing the commission of crimes within the jurisdiction of the Tribal Court. In such cases, the petition filed under this Code shall be dismissed, and or a criminal complaint shall be filed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>An individual at least eighteen years of age who committed either a class 4 or class 5 offense and/or a sexual crime while a child and was not adjudicated for the offense in juvenile court may be prosecuted in adult court as an adult, unless the Tribe intentionally delayed the prosecution to avoid juvenile court jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </codify:replace>
</document>
