<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>13B</num>
  <heading>Recall, Referendum and Constitutional Amendments</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>13.12</num>
    <heading>Placeholder</heading>
    <section>
      <num>13.1201</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The right of the enrolled members of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians to elect representatives to protect and promote the best interests of all Tribal members is an important right. Along with the right to elect, is the right to refer to the voters any enacted or proposed resolution or ordinance; propose constitutional amendments; and to recall any representative who has demonstrated the inability or unwillingness to carry out their elected responsibility. The following process is adopted to protect these rights. The following process is not designed to be used as a manner of harassing, vexing or annoying an elected official nor an elected government. It shall be the right of any Qualified Voter to petition the Turtle Mountain Tribal Court any time they may believe that this process is being utilized for any reason not consistent with <cite path="13B|13.12|13.1201">this section</cite>, for a determination of that issue. If the Turtle Mountain Tribal Court determines, after notice and hearing, that the process is being used for a purpose inconsistent with <cite path="13B|13.12|13.1201">this section</cite>, it may enjoin the petitioners from further proceeding with such action.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1202</num>
      <heading>Remedy for Misuse of Recall Process</heading>
      <text>It shall be the right of any Qualified voter to petition the Turtle Mountain Tribal Court, any time they believe that this process is being utilized for any reason not consistent with <cite path="13B|13.12|13.1202">this section</cite>, for a determination of that issue.  If the Turtle Mountain Tribal Court determined, after notice and hearing, that the process is being used for a purpose inconsistent with <cite path="13B|13.12|13.1202">this section</cite>, it may enjoin the petitioners from further proceeding with such action.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1203</num>
      <heading>Recall of District Official</heading>
      <text>Recall of a representative elected by district vote shall be instituted by a petition signed by a number of qualified voters equal to twenty percent (20<strong>%</strong>) of the total votes cast in the last general election.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1204</num>
      <heading>Recall of At-Large Official</heading>
      <text>Recall of an official who is elected by the voters at large, shall be instituted by a petition signed by a number of qualified voters equal to twenty percent (20<strong>%</strong>) of the total votes cast in the last general election.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1205</num>
      <heading>Recall, Referendum and Constitutional Amendment</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Recall Petition. An election to vote on whether a particular official should be removed from office must be initiated by a recall petition in the following form:</text>
        <text class="center">
          <u>RECALL PETITION</u>
        </text>
        <text>We, the undersigned qualified voters of the Turtle Mountain Chippewa Band of Chippewa Indians of North Dakota do hereby petition the Turtle Mountain Chippewa Tribal Council, pursuant to the Article VIII, Section 2, of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians of North Dakota, to call a recall election for the purpose of removing <u>_________(Name)_____________________</u> from office.  The reason(s) for removal:</text>
        <text>____________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to signers:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Signers of this petition must individually sign their names in the form in which they are registered to vote.</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to circulators:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Before the petition is filed, each circulator must ensure the petition includes: the district of the voter, the residence address and date of birth of the signer (if the signer does not have a designated street address, a post office box must be included), the date of signing, and must legibly print the name of the signer in the space provided. Abbreviations of common usage may be used. Ditto marks may not be used.</text>
        <text>Failure to provide all information requested may invalidate the signature.</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>(Signature)				(Address)				(Date)</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>Print Name		City or Town	District		Date of Birth</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Referendum Petition. A referendum may be requested by one of the following means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Passage of a resolution showing an affirmative vote of five (5) members of the Tribal Council; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Submission of the following referendum petition form:</text>
          <text class="center">
            <u>REFERENDUM PETITION</u>
          </text>
        </para>
        <text>We, the undersigned members of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians do hereby demand that the Turtle Mountain Chippewa Tribal Council, pursuant to Article VIII Section 1, of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians of North Dakota, call a referendum election for the purposes of referring to a vote of the eligible voters of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians resolution or ordinance number [specify Resolution or Ordinance and number] passed or proposed by the Tribal Council on [Date], which was passed or proposed for the purpose of: [indicate purpose of resolution or ordinance].</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to signers:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Signers of this petition must individually sign their names in the form in which they are registered to vote.</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to circulators:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Before the petition is filed, each circulator must ensure the petition includes: the district of the voter, the residence address and date of birth of the signer (if the signer does not have a designated street address, a post office box must be included), the date of signing, and must legibly print the name of the signer in the space provided. Abbreviations of common usage may be used. Ditto marks may not be used.</text>
        <text>Failure to provide all information requested may invalidate the signature.</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>(Signature)				(Address)				(Date)</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>Print Name		City or Town	District		Date of Birth</text>
        <text>Upon passage of such a resolution or notification of the Bureau of Indian Affairs Enrollment Officer under ยง13.1205 of <cite path="13B">this Title</cite>, the Tribal Council shall call for a referendum election. The Election Board shall hold the election within thirty (30) days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Constitutional Amendment Petition. The following constitutional amendment petition format shall be used in all efforts of the people to request the tribal governing body to call an election for purposes of amending the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Constitution and Bylaws:</text>
        <text class="center">
          <u>CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT PETITION</u>
        </text>
        <text>We, the undersigned resident voters of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians do hereby demand the Turtle Mountain Chippewa Tribal Council, pursuant to Article XIII Section 2, of the Turtle Mountain Chippewa Tribal Constitution, call an election for the purposes of putting to a vote of the qualified voters of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians the following constitutional amendment:</text>
        <text class="center">[Insert text of proposed amendment]</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to signers:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Signers of this petition must individually sign their names in the form in which they are registered to vote.</text>
        <text>
          <u>Instructions to circulators:</u>
        </text>
        <text>Before the petition is filed, each circulator must ensure the petition includes: the district of the voter, the residence address and date of birth of the signer (if the signer does not have a designated street address, a post office box must be included), the date of signing, and must legibly print the name of the signer in the space provided. Abbreviations of common usage may be used. Ditto marks may not be used.</text>
        <text>Failure to provide all information requested may invalidate the signature.</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>(Signature)				(Address)				(Date)</text>
        <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
        <text>Print Name		City or Town	District		Date of Birth</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 916-09-14"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1206</num>
      <heading>Presentation of Petitions for Recall, Referendum and Constitutional Amendments</heading>
      <text>Original petitions for recall, referendum and constitutional amendment shall be presented to the Tribal Council by a qualified voter at an open public meeting convened by the Chairperson, or in the absence of the Chairperson, by the Vice-Chairperson.  The Council or the Chairperson shall accept the petitions, noting the acceptance of the petitions in the record. Photocopies of petitions shall not be accepted. If the Chairperson is the person being recalled, then the petitions shall be accepted by the Secretary-Treasurer of the Tribal Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>In the case of recall petitions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Chairperson shall turn the petitions over to the Chairperson of the Election Board, or, in the absence of the Election Board Chairperson, his or her duly authorized representative from the Election Board who shall secure such recall petitions by placing them in the custody of the Bureau of Indian Affairs safe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The Election Board shall meet within seven (7) days to review any recall petitions submitted in accordance with ยง13.1204(2)(A). Such review shall include verifying whether signatures contained on the petition are those of qualified voters and determining the total number of qualified voters' signatures contained on the petition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>If the recall petition satisfies the requirements set out in <cite path="13B">this Title</cite>, the Election Board shall immediately publish notice of a recall election to be held no sooner than fifteen (15) days after such notice, but no later than thirty (30) days after such notice.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>After receipt and verification of the original recall petitions, the Election Chairperson, or his/her duly authorized representative of the Election Board, shall secure and maintain all records by depositing the same with the Bureau of Indian Affairs for placement in a locked vault for sixty (60) days in case there is a contested matter, in which case the records shall be retained until there is a final adjudication of the matter.  Thereafter, all records shall be destroyed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>In the case of referendum or constitutional amendment petitions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Chairperson shall accept the original petitions, noting the acceptance of the petitions in the record. Photocopies of petitions shall not be accepted. After accepting the petitions, the Council or Chairperson, acting on behalf of the Council, shall turn such petitions over to the Chairperson of the Election Board or, in the absence of the Election Board Chairperson, his or duly authorized representative from the Election Board who shall secure such recall petitions by placing them in the custody of the Bureau of Indian Affairs safe. The Enrollment Officer shall secure such petitions and determine the number of qualified voters' signatures contained therein. The Enrollment Officer shall immediately notify the Council as to whether the petitions contain a sufficient number of qualified voters' signatures to call a referendum or constitutional amendment election as required under <cite path="13B">this Title</cite> and/or the Constitution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The Election Board shall hold the election within thirty (30) days and shall publish a notice of the same at least fifteen (15) days prior to such election.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The Election Board shall meet within seven (7) days to review any referendum or constitutional amendment petitions submitted in accordance with ยง13.1205.  Such review shall include verifying whether signatures contained on the petition are those of qualified voters and determining the total number of qualified voters' signatures contained on the petition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>If the referendum or constitutional amendment petition satisfies the requirements set out in <cite path="13B">this Title</cite>, the Election Board shall immediately publish notice of a recall election to be held no sooner than fifteen (15) days after such notice, but no later than thirty (30) days after such notice.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Determining Referendum Election. The majority of the votes cast in a referendum election shall be conclusive and binding on the Tribal Council. If the resolution or ordinance is rejected by such vote, such resolution or ordinance shall be null and void as of the date of the referendum and shall not be reconsidered for a period of at least six (6) months.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Determining Constitutional Amendment Election. The majority of the votes cast in a constitutional amendment election shall be conclusive and binding, and the amendment shall take effect immediately or as otherwise specified on the election ballot, provided that at least twenty percent (20%) of the resident voters of the Tribe entitled to vote shall vote in such election and that the amendment is approved in accordance with Article XIII of the Constitution.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>All original petitions shall be, after verification, delivered to the Election Board Chairperson who shall deposit the same with the Bureau of Indian Affairs for placement in a locked vault until sixty (60) days after any election called based upon such petitions unless there is a contested election in which case the records shall be retained until there is a final adjudication of the matter. Thereafter the original petitions shall be destroyed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 916-09-14"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1207</num>
      <heading>Notice of Recall, Referendum or Constitutional Amendment Election</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>A notice of a recall, referendum or constitutional amendment election shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>the date of the election;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>location of the polling places;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>time the polls shall be open; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>the name(s) of the officer(s) to be recalled, the issue to be referred, or the proposed constitutional amendment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>A recall ballot shall be in the following form:</text>
        <text class="center">RECALL BALLOT</text>
        <text>A petition for recall of _________________________________________________</text>
        <text>(Officer's Name)</text>
        <text>Who holds the office of __________________________________________________</text>
        <text>(Office/Title)</text>
        <text>Had been received by the Tribal Council and validated by the Election Board.</text>
        <text>_______ Yes	A "YES" vote is "<u>IN FAVOR</u>" of removing _______________________</text>
        <text>(Name)</text>
        <text>_______ No	A "NO" vote is "<u>AGAINST</u>" removing ____________________________</text>
        <text>(Name)</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The referendum ballot shall be in the following form:</text>
        <text class="center">REFERENDUM BALLOT</text>
        <text>Resolution/Ordinance number [specify Resolution or Ordinance and number] proposed to be passed by the Tribal Council or passed by the Tribal Council or [specify date passed], for the purpose of: [indicate purpose of resolution or ordinance] has been referred to a vote of the qualified voters of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
        <text>_______ Yes	A "YES" vote is "<u>IN FAVOR</u>" of keeping the Tribal Council</text>
        <text>resolution or ordinance (Number) in effect.</text>
        <text>_______ No A "NO" vote is "<u>AGAINST</u>" keeping the Tribal Council resolution or</text>
        <text>ordinance (number) and prohibiting the Tribal Council from enacting</text>
        <text>or reconsidering the legislation for a period of six (6) months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>A constitutional amendment ballot shall be in the following form:</text>
        <text class="center">
          <u>CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT BALLOT</u>
        </text>
        <text>[Article  <u>__</u> Section  	] of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Constitution and Bylaws currently reads:</text>
        <text>[insert text of current constitutional provision at issue] By a petition received by the Tribal Council and validated by the Bureau of Indian Affairs it has been proposed that [Article     Section ___] be amended to read as follows:</text>
        <text>[insert proposed amended text]</text>
        <text>_______ Yes A "YES" vote is <u>"IN FAVOR"</u> of amending</text>
      </para>
      <text>Article _______Section _______.</text>
      <text>_______ No A "NO" vote is <u>"AGAINST"</u> amending</text>
      <text>Article _______Section _______.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>13.1208</num>
      <heading>Vacancy in Office</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Council by an affirmative vote of the majority shall appoint a replacement to fill any vacancy of a district representative or other elected officer, caused by removal, recall, death, or resignation, provided the term of the replacement shall not extend beyond the next regular election regardless of the length of the unexpired term.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
