<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>29</num>
  <heading>Corporate Code</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>29.01</num>
    <heading>General Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.010</num>
      <heading>Scope</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>This provisions of <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall apply to all corporations which are formed under the laws and sovereign power of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, regardless of ownership and regardless whether formed before or after this Act goes into effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="29">this Title</cite> apply to all corporations operating within the Territory of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.010 was formerly codified as 29.0101</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.020</num>
      <heading>Purpose and Construction</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The purposes of <cite path="29">this Title</cite> are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To encourage commerce;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To reform and develop the laws of business organizations and corporations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>To ensure that corporate assets, but not those generally of the Tribe, are available for the satisfaction of valid claims of corporate creditors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To simplify, clarify, and modernize the laws applicable to both for-profit and non-profit corporations chartered or created under the sovereign powers of the Tribe; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>To facilitate the creation of business organizations for private citizens to form their own corporations to gain the benefits of corporate business.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall be construed and applied with deference to business development.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.020 was formerly codified as 29.0102</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.030</num>
      <heading>General Powers</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians has inherent sovereignty to enter into business relations as it deems consistent with the best interests of the Tribe. The Tribe may enter into business relationships, including but not limited to, as the Tribe itself, as an Tribal Business of the Tribe operating under a doing business as name, as a corporation, as a limited liability company, joint venture, or other business organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Corporations may be organized under <cite path="29">this Title</cite> for any lawful purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>General Powers. Unless its Articles of Incorporation provide otherwise, every corporation shall have the following powers:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To exist perpetually;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To sue and be sued and to complain or defend in its corporate name, except that the extent of the corporation's liability shall be limited to the assets of the corporation or insured coverage, and shall be subject to the limitations contained in <cite path="29">this Title</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>To have a corporate seal, which may be altered at will, and to use it or a facsimile of it by impressing or affixing it or in any manner reproduce it;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To purchase, receive, lease, or otherwise acquire, and own, hold, improve, use, and otherwise deal with real or personal property, or any interest in property wherever located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>To sell, convey, mortgage, pledge, lease, exchange, and otherwise dispose of all or any part of its property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>To purchase, receive, subscribe for, or otherwise acquires, own, hold, vote, use, sell, mortgage, lend, pledge, or otherwise dispose of and deal in and with shares or other interests in or obligations of any other entity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>To make contracts and incur liabilities, borrow money, issue notes, bonds, and other obligations, and secure any of its obligations by mortgage or pledge of any of its property, franchises, and income;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>To lend money, invest its funds, and receive and hold real and personal property as security for repayment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>To be a promoter, partner, member, associate, or manager of any partnership, joint venture, trust, or other entity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>To conduct its business, locate offices, and exercise the powers granted by <cite path="29">this Title</cite> within or without land held in trust for the Nation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>To elect or appoint officers and agents of the corporation, define their duties and fix their compensation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <text>To pay pensions and establish pension plans, trusts, profit sharing plans, share bonus plans, and benefit or incentive plans for any or all its current or former directors, officers, and employees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(13)</num>
          <text>To indemnify any director or officer against their expenses incurred in connection with the defense of any action suit or proceeding in which they are a party by reason of their service with the corporation, except in cases where the director or officer is adjudged liable for negligence or misconduct in the performance of duty;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(14)</num>
          <text>To make and amend bylaws, not inconsistent with its articles of incorporation or with the laws of the Tribe, for managing the business and regulating the affairs of the corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(15)</num>
          <text>To make donations for the public welfare or for charitable, scientific, or educational purposes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(16)</num>
          <text>To transact any lawful business that will aid governmental policy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(17)</num>
          <text>To have and exercise all powers necessary or convenient to effect its purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Applicable Law. Any Corporation established pursuant to <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall be bound by all applicable laws of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.030 was formerly codified as 29.0103</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.040</num>
      <heading>Definitions</heading>
      <text>In <cite path="29">this Title</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Address.  "Address" means mailing address, including a zip code.  In the case of a registered office or principal executive office, the term means the mailing address and the actual office location which shall not be a post office box.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Articles.  "Articles" means, in the case of a corporation incorporated under or governed by <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, articles of incorporation, articles of amendment, a resolution of election to become governed by <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, a statement of change of registered office, registered agent, or name of registered agent, a statement establishing or fixing the rights and preferences of a class or series of shares, a statement of cancellation of authorized shares, articles of merger, articles of abandonment, and articles of dissolution.  In the case of a foreign corporation, the term includes all documents serving a similar function required to be filed with the Tribal Secretary or other officer of the Tribe or delegated to a an authorized Department of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Board.  "Board" means the board of directors of a corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Court.  "Court" means the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Director.  "Director" means a member of the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Distribution.  "Distribution" means a direct or indirect transfer of money or other property, other than its own shares, with or without consideration or an incurrence or issuance of indebtedness, by a corporation to any of its shareholders in respect of its shares.  A distribution may be in the form of a dividend or a distribution in liquidation, or as consideration for the purchase, redemption, or other acquisition of its shares, or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Filed with the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer.  "Filed with the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer" means that an original of a document meeting the applicable requirements of <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, signed and accompanied by a filing fee of $50.00, has been delivered to the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer of the Tribe on the Reservation.  The Tribal Secretary/Treasurer shall endorse on the original the word "Filed" and the month, day, year, and time of filing, record the document in the office of the Tribal Secretary, and return the document to the person who delivered it for filing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Foreign corporations.  "Foreign corporations" means a corporation organized for profit that is incorporated under another sovereign's laws, not the laws of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>For-Profit Corporation. "For Profit Corporation" means a corporation of which the income is distributable for the benefit of the shareholders and owners, and whose assets, upon dissolution, are distributable to the shareholders and owners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Good faith.  "Good faith" means honesty in fact in the conduct of the act or transaction concerned, faithfulness to the duties of the office or position, professional conduct which meets the standards of the professions standards, and an absence of intent to defraud or seek unconscionable advantage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Intentionally.  "Intentionally" means that the person referred to either has a purpose to do or fail to perform the act or cause the result specified or believes that the act or failure to act, if successful, will cause that result.  A person "intentionally" violates a law if the person intentionally does the act or causes the result prohibited by the law, or if the person intentionally fails to do the act or cause the result required by the law, even though the person may not know of the existence or constitutionality of the law or the scope or meaning of the terms used in the law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>Joint Venture. "Joint Venture" means a business dealing or undertaking by two or more persons or two or more business with a defined project which shall have four elements: 1.) an express or implied agreement; 2.) a common purpose that the group intends to carry out; 3.) shared profits and losses; and 4.) each member's equal voice in controlling the project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>Know; knowledge.  A person "knows" or has "knowledge" of a fact when the person has actual knowledge of it.  A person does not "know" or "have knowledge" of a fact merely because the person has reason to know of the fact.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>Legal representative.  "Legal representative" means a person empowered to act for another person, including, but not limited to, an agent, officer, partner, or associate of, an organization; a trustee of a trust; a personal representative; an executor of a will; an administrator of an estate; a trustee in bankruptcy; and a receiver, guardian, custodian, or conservator of the person or estate of a person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>Non-Profit Corporation. "Non-Profit Corporation" means a corporation in which no part of the income of the corporation is distributable to any person by reason of that person's status as a member, director, officer or employee, except for reasonable wages for work performed, and whose assets, upon dissolution, are distributable to the shareholders and owners, and organized for a public purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(p)</num>
        <text>Non-Stock Corporation. "Non-Stock Corporation" means a corporation that does not issue shares or stock constituting ownership but is owned by members in accordance with its charter or other written agreement</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(q)</num>
        <text>Notice.  "Notice" is given by a shareholder of a corporation to the corporation or an officer of the corporation when in writing and mailed or delivered to the corporation or the officer at the registered office or principal executive office of the corporation.  In all other cases, "notice" is given to a person when mailed to the person at an address designated by the person or at the last known address of the person, or when communicated to the person orally, or when handed to the person, or when left at the office of the person with a clerk or other person in charge of the office, or if there is no one in charge, when left in a conspicuous place in the office, or if the office is closed or the person to be notified has no office, when left at the dwelling house or usual place of abode of the person with some person of suitable age and discretion then residing therein.  Notice by mail is given when deposited in the United States mail with sufficient postage affixed.  Notice is deemed received when it is given.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(r)</num>
        <text>Private Corporation. "Private Corporation" means any corporation formed by private citizens or private business organizations under the laws of the Tribe who avail themselves to the jurisdiction of the Tribe's courts, either enrolled members or otherwise citizens of the Tribe. A private Corporation is not owned by the Tribe, but the organizers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(s)</num>
        <text>Officer.  "Officer" means a person elected, appointed, or otherwise designated as an officer by the board, and any other person deemed elected by the Board of Directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(t)</num>
        <text>Organization.  "Organization" means a tribal or foreign corporation, foreign limited liability company, limited partnership, joint venture, association, business trust, estate, trust, enterprise, and any other legal or commercial entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(u)</num>
        <text>Parent.  "Parent" of a specified corporation means a corporation that directly, or indirectly through related corporations, owns more than 50 percent of the voting power of the shares entitled to vote for directors of the specified corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(v)</num>
        <text>Person.  "Person" includes a natural person and an organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(w)</num>
        <text>Principal executive office.  "Principal executive office" means an office where the elected or appointed chief executive officer of a corporation has an office.  If the corporation has no elected or appointed chief executive officer, "principal executive office" means the registered office of the corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(x)</num>
        <text>Registered office.  "Registered office" means the place designated in the articles of a corporation as the registered office of the corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(y)</num>
        <text>Related corporation.  "Related corporation" of a specified corporation means a parent or subsidiary of the specified corporation or another subsidiary of a parent of the specified corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(z)</num>
        <text>Reservation.  "Reservation" means the reservation of the Tribe as is now or hereafter may be recognized by the Secretary of the Interior of the United States of America.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(aa)</num>
        <text>Security.  "Security" means any note; stock; treasury stock; bond; debenture; evidence of indebtedness; certificate of interest or participation in any profit sharing agreement; collateral trust certificate; pre-organization certificate or subscription; transferable shares; investment contract; investment metal contract or investment gem contract; voting trust certificate; certificate of deposit for a security; certificate of interest or participation in an oil, gas or mining right, title or lease or in payments out of production under the right, title or lease; or in general, any interest or instrument commonly known as security, or any certificate of interest or participation in, temporary or interim certificate for, receipt for guarantee of, or warrant or right to subscribe to or purchase, any of the foregoing.  "Security" does not include any insurance or endowment policy or annuity contract under which an insurance company promises to pay money either in a lump sum or periodically for life or for some other specified period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(bb)</num>
        <text>Share.  "Share" means one of the units, however designated, into which the shareholders proprietary interests in a corporation are divided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(cc)</num>
        <text>Shareholder.  "Shareholder" means a person registered on the books or records of a corporation or its transfer agent or registrar as the owner of whole or fractional shares of the corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(dd)</num>
        <text>Signed.  "Signed" means that the signature of a person has been written on a document and, with respect to a document required by this Code "to be filed with the Tribal Secretary," means that the document has been signed by a person authorized to do so by this Code, the articles or bylaws, or a resolution approved by the affirmative vote of the required proportion or number of the directors or the holders of the required proportion or number of the voting power of the shares present and entitled to vote.  A signature on a document not required by this Code to be filed with the Tribal Secretary may be a facsimile affixed, engraved, printed, placed, stamped with indelible ink, or in any other manner reproduced on the document.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(ee)</num>
        <text>Subsidiary.  "Subsidiary" of a specified corporation means a corporation having more than 50 percent of the voting power of its shares entitled to vote for directors owned directly, or indirectly through related corporations, by the specified corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(ff)</num>
        <text>Territory. "Territory" means the geographical area that the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians exercises jurisdiction over.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(gg)</num>
        <text>"Tribal Business."  "Tribal Business" is any business owned and operated by the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa in which the Tribe has an interest, this includes, but is not limited to, a casino doing business for the Tribe with a Doing Business As name, a corporation, Joint venture, or limited liability company.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(hh)</num>
        <text>Tribal Corporation. "Tribal Corporation" includes any entity created and owned by the Tribe for economic or governmental purposes. These corporations are owned by the Tribe and their assets and operation are subject to the Tribe's laws, regulations, and policies. Tribal Corporations shall not be filed with the State of North Dakota in any manner unless it is operating as a foreign corporation within the State of North Dakota.  There shall be three types of Tribal Corporations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A for profit public corporation held and controlled by the Tribe designed to create profit for the Tribe's benefit with the issuance of shares or stock;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A for profit non-stock corporation held and controlled by a Board specifically delegated with the authority to manage the affairs of the corporation.  All for profit non-stock corporations shall create profit solely to benefit the Tribe, reinvest in the community, and sustain and grow itself for these purposes.  The terms of Board members shall be specifically enumerated in the formation documents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A non-profit corporation held by the Tribe with control delegated to a Board or Commission by law and specifically appointed by the Tribe to manage control of the non-profit corporation's assets.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(ii)</num>
        <text>Tribal Council.  "Tribal Council" means the Tribal Council of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(jj)</num>
        <text>Tribal Secretary.  "Tribal Secretary" means the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer for the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(kk)</num>
        <text>Tribe.  "Tribe" means the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(ll)</num>
        <text>Trust land.  "Trust land" means land held in trust by the United States government for the benefit of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 246-05-17"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.040 was formerly codified as 29.0104</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.050</num>
      <heading>Tax Status of All Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For purposes of taxations, regulatory jurisdiction and civil jurisdiction, all tribal corporations created pursuant to the sovereign powers of the Tribe for the benefit of the Tribe shall be deemed to be a subordinate arm of the government of the Tribe and shall be entitled to all of the privileges and immunities of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction to decide all questions with respect to the status of a tribal corporation formed pursuant to the sovereign powers of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction to decide all questions of jurisdiction, choice of law, and dispute resolution mechanism over transaction between corporations operating within the Territory of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.050 was formerly codified as 29.0105</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.060</num>
      <heading>Pre-Existing Tribal Corporation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A Tribal entity preexisting passage of <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall continue to exist and to perform its several functions, but will be issued a tribal corporation charter pursuant to <cite path="29">this Title</cite> within a reasonable time.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All pre-existing corporations shall annually file renewals just as newly formed corporations are required.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.060 was formerly codified as 29.0106</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.070</num>
      <heading>Sovereign Immunity Waiver</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Only Tribal Corporations enjoy sovereign immunity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Sovereign immunity of the Tribal Corporation. A tribal corporation maintains all the inherent vestiges of sovereignty that the Tribe enjoys.</text>
        <text>Pursuant to its inherent sovereignty the Tribe enjoys sovereign immunity from suit which has been reaffirmed by Federal case law and statute.  The Tribal Corporation is clothed with all the privileges and immunities of the Tribe, except as specifically limited by the Tribal Corporation's Charter, including sovereign immunity from suit in any tribal, federal or state court. Nothing in <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall be deemed or construed to be a waiver of sovereign immunity of a tribal entity from suit or to be a consent of the tribal entity of the Tribe, to the jurisdiction of the United States or of any state with regard to the business or affairs of the tribal entity or to any cause of action, cause or controversy, except as provided herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Waiver of Sovereign Immunity of the Tribal Corporation. Sovereign immunity of the tribal corporation may be waived only be express resolution of the governing body of the tribal corporation. All waivers of sovereign immunity must be preserved with the resolution of the governing body of the tribal corporation of continuing force and effect. Waivers of sovereign immunity are disfavored and shall be granted only when necessary to secure a substantial advantage or benefit to the tribal entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Waivers of sovereign immunity shall not be general but shall be specific and limited as to duration, grantee, transaction, property or funds, if any, of the tribal corporation subject thereto, court having jurisdiction pursuant thereto and law applicable thereunder. Nothing in a tribal corporation charter shall be deemed or construed to be a waiver of sovereign immunity from suit of the Tribe or to be a consent of the Tribe to the jurisdiction of the United States or of any state with regard to the business or affairs of the tribal corporation or the Tribe or to any cause of action, case or affairs of the tribal corporation or the Tribe or to any cause of action, case or controversy, except as provided herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Credit of the Tribe. Nothing in a tribal corporate charter, nor any activity of any tribal entity, shall implicate or in any way involve the credit of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Inclusion in Charter. The provisions of Subsection (a) through (e) of <cite path="§29.01.070">this Section</cite> shall be, by operation of law, be included in the charter of each existing tribal corporation, and shall be expressly stated in the charter of all tribal entities hereinafter acquired or created.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 246-05-17"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.070 was formerly codified as 29.0107</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.080</num>
      <heading>Assets of a Tribal Corporation</heading>
      <text>A tribal corporation shall have only those assets of the Tribe formally assigned to it by the Tribal Council, together with whatever assets it acquires from other sources. No activity of a tribal corporation nor any indebtedness incurred by it shall implicate or in any way involve any assets of tribal members or the Tribe not assigned in writing to the tribal corporation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.080 was formerly codified as 29.0108</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.090</num>
      <heading>Tribal Secretary's Authority to Charter Corporations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council hereby delegates to the Secretary/Treasurer and the Secretary/Treasurer is hereby authorized to charter corporations to operate within the jurisdiction of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Secretary/Treasurer shall be authorized a budget to carry out the intent of <cite path="29">this Title</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Secretary/Treasurer may hire necessary staff in order to effectuate the purposes of <cite path="29">this Title</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Secretary/Treasurer is authorized to collect fees from incorporators subject to the terms of this act.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.090 was formerly codified as 29.0109</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.100</num>
      <heading>Service on Corporation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A corporation's registered agent is the corporation's agent for service of process, notice or demand required or permitted by law to be served on the corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in sub. (c), if a corporation has no registered agent or the agent cannot with reasonable diligence be served, the corporation may be served by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested, addressed to the corporation at its principal office. Service is perfected under this subsection at the earliest of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The date on which the corporation receives the mail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The date shown on the return receipt, if signed on behalf of the corporation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Five days after its deposit in the U.S. mail, if mailed postpaid and correctly addressed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, if the address of the corporation's principal office cannot be determined from the records held by the department, the corporation may be served by publishing a notice, in the newspaper where the corporation's principal office or registered office, as most recently designated in the Tribe's records, is located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text><cite path="§29.01.100">This section</cite> does not limit or affect the right to serve any process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served on a corporation in any other manner permitted by law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.100 was formerly codified as 29.0110</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.110</num>
      <heading>Denial of Issuance of a Corporate Charter</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Secretary/Treasurer may deny issuance of a Corporate Charter, if he or she determines that the Corporate Charter does not comport with the law. The Tribal Secretary/Treasurer shall give written notice of the reason for the denial of the issuance of the charter citing specific provisions of this code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.110 was formerly codified as 29.0111</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.120</num>
      <heading>Funding</heading>
      <text>In accordance with its inherent sovereignty and in the spirit of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act, 25 U.S.C. 450 <em>et seq</em>., the tribal corporations may solicit funding via grants from the Secretary of the Interior, other agencies, and private funding sources in furtherance of its purpose.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.120 was formerly codified as 29.0112</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.130</num>
      <heading>Records of the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>All records required or allowed to be maintained by the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer are Tribal Government records and shall be public records.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Removing, tampering with, or destroying any record in a hard or electronic copy to thwart the purpose of this Act shall be unlawful and punishable to a term of imprisonment of one (1) day and up to but not to exceed one (1) year or a fine minimum of one hundred dollars ($100) and not to exceed five thousand dollars ($5,000) or both, enforceable by the BIA Tribal Law Enforcement, the Turtle Mountain Tribal Law Enforcement, and the Tribal Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.130 was formerly codified as 29.0113</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.140</num>
      <heading>Registration Required for Foreign Corporations</heading>
      <text>Foreign corporations doing business within the Territory of the TMBCI are required to annually pay a $50 fee for doing business within the jurisdiction of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.140 was formerly codified as 29.0114</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.150</num>
      <heading>Severability</heading>
      <text>In the event that any provision of this Law or the application thereof to any person or circumstances is held invalid, the remainder of this Law shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.150 was formerly codified as 29.0115</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.160</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this Law shall be effective date of adoption and shall remain in effect until repealed or amended.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.160 was formerly codified as 29.0116</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.170</num>
      <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Existing Law</heading>
      <text>Any law or resolution enacted prior to this code which is inconsistent with its enforcement is hereby repealed.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.170 was formerly codified as 29.0117</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.01.180</num>
      <heading>Rules and Regulations</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Secretary/Treasurer shall enact rules and regulation to facilitate the enforcement of this Corporations Code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.01.180 was formerly codified as 29.0118</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>29.02</num>
    <heading>Tribally Owned Corporations</heading>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.010</num>
      <heading>Corporate Charter for Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The charter for a Tribal Corporation formed under <cite path="29">this Title</cite> shall set forth:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The name of the tribal corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The purposes for which the Tribal Corporation is organized, including but not limited to creating profits for the benefit of the Tribe and reinvesting in the community;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The manner by which the Tribe will ensure that the Tribal Corporation benefits the Tribe and the community, consistent with Section 29.0214 of <cite path="29">this Title</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The terms of the members of the Board of Directors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The service address for the corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The powers of the tribal corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The specific designation of which type of tribal corporation it is as enumerated in the definition of tribal corporation, herein;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>The provisions of 29.0107 above, providing for sovereign immunity and waivers thereof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>Provisions directing management of the tribal corporation and regulation of its affairs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Provisions designed to insulate the tribal corporation from the shifts of policy of tribal politics.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The charter must designate whether shares shall be issued.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 246-05-17"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.010 was formerly codified as 29.0201</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.020</num>
      <heading>Delegation of Essential Governmental Functions to Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <text>For purposes of allowing a tribal corporation to utilize the provisions of the Tribal Governmental Tax Status Act of 1982, as amended, the Tribal Council may delegate one or more essential governmental functions to a tribal corporation, provided that the exercise of any such power shall be within the powers delegated to the tribal corporation by law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.020 was formerly codified as 29.0202</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.030</num>
      <heading>Liability of Members of Governing Body of Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <text>No member of the governing body of any tribal corporation formed pursuant to the sovereign powers of the Tribe shall be liable to any creditor of the tribal corporation by reason of his status as such a member, or by reason of acts done in the course of his official duties. No member of the governing body of the tribal corporation shall have the authority to individually bind the corporation without a specific delegation by the Board of Directors or by law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.030 was formerly codified as 29.0203</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.040</num>
      <heading>Article of Incorporation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The articles of incorporation for all corporations formed pursuant to <cite path="29">this TItle</cite> shall set forth the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The name of the Corporation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The period of existence, which may be perpetual.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The purpose for which the corporation is organized, which may include the transaction of any or lawful business for which corporations may be incorporated under <cite path="29">this Title</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Any provision not inconsistent with law which the incorporators elect to set forth in the Article of Incorporation for the regulation of the internal affairs of the Corporation, including any provision restricting the transfer of shares and any provision which under <cite path="29">this Title</cite> is required or permitted to be set forth in the bylaws.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The address of its initial registered office and the name of its initial registered agent at such address.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The number of directors constituting the initial board of directors and the names and addresses of the persons who are to serve as directors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The name and address of each incorporator.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>If a corporation is authorized pursuant to its Articles of Incorporation to create and issue shares of stock, the articles of incorporation shall also set forth the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The number of shares which the corporation shall have authority to issue and a description of their classes if any and par value if any.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>If the shares are to be divided into classes, the designation of each class and a statement of the preferences, limitations, and relative rights in respect of the shares of each class.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>If the corporation is to issue the shares of any preferred or special class in series, then the designation of each series and a statement of the variations in the relative rights and preferences between series and a statement of the authority of the board of directors to designate such rights and preferences over time.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>If any preemptive right is to be granted to shareholders, the provisions therefore.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>It shall not be necessary to set forth in the Articles of Incorporation any of the corporate powers enumerated in <cite path="29">this Title</cite>. Whenever a provision of the Articles of Incorporation is inconsistent with the bylaws, the Articles shall be controlling and year of the filing thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>If a corporation is to be owned and operated in whole or in part by the Tribe, the Tribe must approve the article of incorporation according to its own procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Filing of Articles of Incorporation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Duplicate originals of the articles of incorporation shall be delivered to the Secretary/Treasurer. If the Secretary/Treasurer finds that the Articles of Incorporation conform to tribal law, the Secretary/Treasurer shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Endorse on each duplicate originals the word "filed" and the month, day, and year of the filing thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Register and maintain one duplicate original in the Tribal Records Office.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Issue a Certificate of Incorporation to which the Secretary/Treasurer shall affix the other duplicate original and return to the incorporators.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Effect of Issuance of Certificate of Incorporation. Unless a delayed effective date is specified, the corporate existence begins when the Certificate of Incorporation is registered.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.040 was formerly codified as 29.0204</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.050</num>
      <heading>Amendment of Tribal Corporation Charter</heading>
      <text>Any tribal corporation chartered under the laws and sovereign power of the Tribe may be amended.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A corporation may amend its articles of incorporation by submitting executed articles of amendment with the Secretary/Treasurer. The articles of amendment shall be approved by the corporation's shareholders and executed by its president or vice president and its secretary. If a corporation is owned and operated in whole or in part by the Tribe, the Tribal Council must approve the amendments by a two-thirds vote.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Duplicate originals of the executed articles of amendment shall be delivered to the Secretary/Treasurer. If the Secretary/Treasurer determines that the articles of amendment conform to tribal law, the Secretary/Treasurer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Endorse on each duplicate original the word "files" and the month, day, and year of such filing thereof.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Register and maintain one such duplicate original in the Legislative Office.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Issue a certificate of amendment to which the Secretary shall affix the other duplicate original and return to the corporation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Upon the issuance of the certificate of amendment by the Secretary, the amendment shall become effective and is conclusive proof that all conditions precedent for amendment of the articles of incorporation have been satisfied.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.050 was formerly codified as 29.0205</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.060</num>
      <heading>Application</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><u>Corporations directly owned by the Tribe</u>.  The consent of the Tribal Council shall be required prior to the incorporation under this Code of any corporation to be wholly owned by the Tribe.  For this purpose, the incorporator shall file with the Tribal Secretary, when the incorporator files the articles of incorporation of a corporation to be wholly owned by the Tribe, a certified copy of a resolution of the Tribal Council authorizing the formation of the corporation</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><u>Corporations indirectly owned by the Tribe</u>.  The consent of the board of directors of the corporation wholly owned by the Tribe shall be required prior to the incorporation under <cite path="29">this Title</cite> of a subsidiary corporation to be wholly owned by a parent corporation that is wholly owned by the Tribe.  For this purpose, the incorporator shall file with the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer, when the incorporator files the articles of incorporation of a subsidiary corporation to be wholly owned by a parent corporation that is wholly owned by the Tribe, a certified copy of a resolution of the board of the parent corporation authorizing the formation of the subsidiary corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.060 was formerly codified as 29.0206</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.070</num>
      <heading>Special Powers, Privileges and Immunities of Corporations Wholly Owned by the Tribe</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><u>Scope.</u>  The special powers, privileges and immunities described in <cite path="§29.02.070">this section</cite> shall be available only to a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><u>Jurisdictional and tax immunities.</u>  All of the rights, privileges and immunities of the Tribe concerning federal, state, or local taxes, regulations and jurisdiction are hereby conferred on all tribal corporations wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe to the same extent that the Tribe would have such rights, privileges and immunities if it engaged in the activities undertaken by the corporation.  Absent consent by the corporation, a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall not be subject to taxation by the Tribe, except to the extent that such taxation is necessary and reasonably appropriate to compensate the Tribe for services and regulations provided to the corporation by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text><u>Sovereign immunity.  </u>The sovereign immunity of the Tribe is hereby conferred on all tribal corporations wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe.  A corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall have the power to sue and is authorized to consent to be sued in the court, and in all other courts of competent jurisdiction, provided, however, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>no such consent to suit shall be effective against the corporation unless such consent is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>explicit,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>contained in a written contract or commercial document to which the corporation is a party, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Specifically approved by the board of directors of the corporation, and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any recovery against such corporation shall be limited to the assets of the corporation.</text>
          <text>Any consent to suit may be limited to the court or courts in which suit may be brought, to the matters that may be made the subject of the suit and to the assets or revenues of the corporation against which any judgment may be executed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.070 was formerly codified as 29.0207</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.080</num>
      <heading>Boards of Tribal Businesses and Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If the Tribal Council Organizes a Tribal Business or Tribal Corporation it shall set forth in the organizing documents how the Board of Directors will be comprised of and how the Board of Directors will be appointed. If the Tribal Council will be the Board of Directors the organizing documents shall enumerate such term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Removal of directors.  A director of a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe may be removed with or without cause by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Loans to directors.  A corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall be prohibited from loaning or lending money to or guaranteeing the personal obligation of a director, officer or employee of the corporation under any circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.080 was formerly codified as 29.0208</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.090</num>
      <heading>Scope of Board Members Authority</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Individual Board members have only the authority to act specifically delegated to them by Board resolution or written action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any delegation of authority to Board member must be done by official Board action in accordance with the Corporation's bylaws.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.090 was formerly codified as 29.0209</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.100</num>
      <heading>Shares in Corporations Wholly Owned by the Tribe; Shareholders; Voting</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><u>Shares in wholly tribally owned corporations.</u>  Share certificates (or transaction statements for uncertificated shares) of corporations wholly owned, directly, by the Tribe shall be issued in the name of the Tribe, and all such shares shall be held by and for the Tribe.  No member of the Tribe shall have any personal ownership interest in any corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe, whether by virtue of such person's status as a member of the Tribe or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><u>Shares.</u>  A corporation wholly owned, directly, by the Tribe may not issue preferred or special shares.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text><u>Voting.</u>  A member of the Tribal Council or Board shall be authorized to vote shares of the corporation owned by the Tribe in the following manner:  Each member shall have the right to vote that number of shares which is equal to a fraction of the total shares owned by the Tribe.  The fraction is calculated by dividing the total number of shares owned by the Tribe by the number of Tribal Council members holding such office at the date on which the vote is taken.  Each member of the Tribal Council shall enjoy such voting rights in the corporation as is provided by the Constitution and bylaws of the Tribe to such person as a member of the Tribal Council.  Such voting rights shall be enjoyed for as long as such council member remains a duly elected member of the Tribal Council.  In voting the shares of a corporation wholly owned by the Tribe, the members of the Tribal Council are acting not in a personal capacity but in a representative capacity on behalf of the Tribe itself and shall have a duty to act in the best interest of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text><u>Proxies illegal.</u>  Any proxy given for the voting of shares in a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall be void and unenforceable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text><u>Voting trusts illegal.</u>  Any voting trust agreement for any interest held in a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall be void and unenforceable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text><u>Shareholder control agreements illegal.</u>  Any shareholder control agreement, sometimes referenced as a pooling agreement, for any interest held in a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe shall be void and unenforceable.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.100 was formerly codified as 29.0210</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.110</num>
      <heading>Liability of Tribe as Shareholder</heading>
      <text>Neither the Tribe nor any member of the Tribal Council nor any Board member shall be under any obligation to a corporation wholly owned, directly or indirectly, by the Tribe or to the creditors of any such corporation and the Tribe shall not be deemed to have waived any of the Tribe's privileges or immunities if the Tribe incorporates, owns or operates a corporation, directly or indirectly.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.110 was formerly codified as 29.0211</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.120</num>
      <heading>Shareholder Meetings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><u>Annual meeting.  </u>Annual meetings of the Board of Directors or Tribal Council acting as the Board of Directors, in its capacity as the shareholders of a corporation wholly owned, directly, by the Tribe, shall be held at such time and at such place on the Reservation as the board of directors shall determine.  If the board of directors fails to set the time and date of meeting, it shall be held on the second Tuesday in February of each year.  At such annual meeting, the Tribal Council, in its capacity as the shareholders of the corporation, shall transact such business as may properly be brought before the meeting.  Such meetings may be called and held in the same manner as applicable law provides for meetings of the Tribal Council if no other bylaw dictates process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><u>Special meetings</u>.  Special meeting of the Tribal Council or the Board of Directors, in its capacity as the shareholders of the corporation, may be called and held for any purpose in the manner provided for the call and holding of special meetings of the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text><u>Notice of meetings</u>.  The board of directors shall notify the Tribal Council of the date, time and place of the annual meeting of shareholders at least 20 days before the meeting and of any special meeting of the shareholders at least five days before the meeting.  Notices shall be deemed to be effective if placed in the U.S. Mail, with proper first class postage affixed, at least 22 days (but not more than 62 days) prior to an annual meeting, and at least 7 days (but not more than 62 days) prior to a special meeting, or on the date personally delivered to the Secretary of the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text><u>Time and place of shareholder's meetings</u>.  Meetings of the shareholders of the corporation shall be held at the principal place of business or of the corporation or at such other location within the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Reservation at such time and place as the board of directors shall fix.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text><u>Manner of meeting</u>.  Except as otherwise provided in the Articles of Incorporation, the shareholders of the corporation may conduct regular or special meetings through the use of any means and procedures which are proper for meetings of the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text><u>Presiding officer</u>.  The Chairman of the Tribal Council or the Chairman of the Board of Directors shall preside over any shareholder's meeting, unless the corporation's Board has been otherwise delegated such authority.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.120 was formerly codified as 29.0212</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.130</num>
      <heading>Assets; Distribution of Income</heading>
      <text>Assets.  Subject to the contractual and sovereign rights of others, including the Tribe, the corporation shall have as its corporate assets, and the authority to acquire, manage, own, use, pledge, encumber, or otherwise dispose of, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>All funds which the corporation may acquire by subscription, grant, gift, loan or other means,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>all interests in real and personal property, whether of a tangible or intangible nature, which the corporation may acquire by subscription, grant, gift, loan, purchase, lease or other means, unless such real property is in trust, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>all earnings, interest, dividends, accumulations, contract rights, claims and other proceeds arising from any of the foregoing.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.130 was formerly codified as 29.0213</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.140</num>
      <heading>Distribution of Net Income to Tribe</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For profit public corporations owned by the Tribe after annually budgeting and evaluation of annual projections shall provide a report of expected income available for distribution to the Tribe. The for profit public corporation shall endeavor to have sufficient operating capitol so that it may be self-sustaining. <cite path="§29.02.140" proof="needed">This section</cite> shall apply to any subsidiaries that the for profit public corporation owns and or controls. Distribution of assets to the Tribe shall be limited by the availability of funds and the ability to sustain itself for a two year period based upon its prior operating budgets and projected income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>For profit non-stock corporations owned by the Tribe after annually budgeting and evaluation of annual projections shall provide a report of expected income available for reinvestment in the corporation and the potential investment for economic development of the community.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.140 was formerly codified as 29.0214</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.150</num>
      <heading>Voluntary Dissolution by Incorporators</heading>
      <text>A corporation wholly owned, directly, by the Tribe with no shares having been issued may be dissolved by a resolution adopted by the incorporators, or if a board of directors has been appointed or elected, by the board of directors and separately concurred in by a majority of the members of the Tribal Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.150 was formerly codified as 29.0215</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.02.160</num>
      <heading>Disposition of Assets for Tribal Corporations</heading>
      <text>Upon dissolution of a tribal corporation its assets shall be distributed at the direction of the Tribal Council, or its designee, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any property held upon an express condition requiring its return, transfer or other disposition shall be distributed accordingly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any property or assets required to be distributed or transferred in any manner according to federal law shall be distributed or transferred accordingly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Claims of creditors of the tribal corporation approved by the Tribal Council shall be paid accordingly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Remaining assets shall be transferred to another tribal corporation, to the Tribe, or distributed or transferred by law enacted by the tribal council.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.02.160 was formerly codified as 29.0216</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>29.03</num>
    <heading>Private Corporations</heading>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.010</num>
      <heading>Private Corporations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A corporation may be formed under <cite path="29.03">this chapter</cite> for any lawful business purpose. The incorporators of any corporation shall include at least one member of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians who is 18 years of age or older.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The signatory on the corporation must be a member of the Tribe with an address within the Territory.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.010 was formerly codified as 29.0301</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.020</num>
      <heading>Corporate Name</heading>
      <text>The name of any corporation formed under <cite path="29.03">this chapter</cite> shall not be the same or similar to any other named corporation formed under <cite path="29">this Title</cite>. The name of the corporation shall end with the word "Corporation" or the word "Incorporated" or the word "Limited" or the abbreviation "Corp.", "Inc." or "Ltd."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.020 was formerly codified as 29.0302</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.030</num>
      <heading>Articles of Incorporation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The incorporators of a corporation must file Articles of Incorporation with the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer and pay a filing fee of $75.00 to the Tribal Finance Office as a prerequisite to incorporation. Such fee shall be annual and shall be filed on the anniversary date of the incorporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Articles of Incorporation must be signed by one or more members of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians who are 18 years of age or older and may include such terms as the Incorporator(s) deem appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Articles shall include, at a minimum, the following:</text>
        <text>ARTICLES OF INCORPORATION</text>
        <text>I (We), the undersigned, being (a member) (members) of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians and being of full age for the purpose of forming a corporation under and pursuant to the provisions of the Law of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians, do hereby adopt the following Articles of Incorporation.</text>
        <text>1. The name of the corporation is _____.</text>
        <text>2. This Corporation is a (stock corporation issuing ____ (# of Shares), a non-stock corporation, or non-profit corporation.)</text>
        <text>3. The purposes of the corporation are as follows:</text>
        <text>a. _____</text>
        <text>b. _____</text>
        <text>c. _____</text>
        <text>4. The period and duration of the corporation shall be ____________ (number of years) (perpetual).</text>
        <text>5. The name of the registered agent, the street address or physical location, and post office address of the registered office of the corporation on the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Reservation is:</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>6. The total number of shares of stock which the corporation shall have the authority to issue shall be determined by resolution by the Board of Directors. The shares of stock may be paid for in money, property or services as prescribed by the Board of Directors.</text>
        <text>7. The amount of capital with which the corporation shall begin a business shall be ____________ ($300.00 or more).</text>
        <text>8. The names, post office addresses, and terms of office of the first directors are as follows:</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>9. The names and post office addresses of the incorporators are as follows:</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>_____</text>
        <text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, (I)(we), have hereunto set (my hand) (our hands) this ____________ day of ____________ 20____________.</text>
        <text>_____<br/>Incorporator</text>
        <text>_____<br/>Incorporator</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.030 was formerly codified as 29.0303</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.040</num>
      <heading>Certificate of Incorporation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Upon filing the Articles of Incorporation and payment of the filing fee, the Tribal Secretary, if the Articles are in conformity with <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, shall issue a Certificate of Incorporation. The Certificate of Incorporation shall be in the following form:</text>
        <text>CERTIFICATE OF INCORPORATION</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, Articles of Incorporation duly signed have been filed in the Tribal  Secretary of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians on the ____________ day of ____________, 20____________, for incorporation of ____________ (name of corporation); and</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, the Articles of Incorporation are in conformity with the requirements of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indian Constitution and laws;</text>
        <text>NOW, THEREFORE, I, _____, Tribal Secretary, do hereby certify that the said ____________ is a legally organized and validly existing corporation under the laws of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
        <text>_______________________________<br/>Tribal Secretary-Treasurer</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Upon the issuance of the Certificate of Incorporation, the corporate existence of the corporation shall begin. Certification assures that the corporation is in compliance with the organizational requirements of <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, but not that the corporation is in compliance with any other provision of law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In the event the Article of Incorporation do not comport with <cite path="29.03">this Chapter</cite> the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer shall issue a Notice of Denial of Corporate Charter in compliance with <cite path="29">this Title</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.040 was formerly codified as 29.0304</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.050</num>
      <heading>Amended Articles of Incorporation</heading>
      <text>A corporation may file Amended Articles of Incorporation, upon approval by its Board of Directors and the shareholders. A filing fee of $50.00 shall accompany that filing, and must be paid to the Tribal Finance Office. Provided those amended articles are consistent with <cite path="29">this Title</cite>, the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer shall issue a Certificate of Amendment to the Corporation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.050 was formerly codified as 29.0305</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.060</num>
      <heading>Bylaws</heading>
      <text>The corporation shall be governed by a set of bylaws. Unless there is submitted to the Tribal Secretary/Treasurer of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians a different form of bylaws, the bylaws shall be as follows:</text>
      <text>BYLAWS OF _____</text>
      <text>
        <em>ARTICLE I. PRINCIPAL PLACE OF BUSINESS</em>
      </text>
      <text>The principal place of business of the corporation shall be located within the boundaries of the Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indian Reservation at the registered office of the corporation.</text>
      <text>
        <em>ARTICLE II. SHAREHOLDERS</em>
      </text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 1. Annual Meetings.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The annual meeting of the shareholders shall be on the 15th day of the month of January each year at 10:00 a.m. at the registered office of the corporation for the purpose of electing directors and for the transaction of any business which may properly come before a meeting of the shareholders. If the annual meeting is not held at the time above designated, an alternative meeting of the shareholders shall be designated by the president of the corporation.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 2. Voting Rights.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>Each owner of a share of stock of the corporation shall be entitled at the meeting of the shareholders to one vote for each share standing in his name. A majority of the outstanding shares of the corporation represented in person shall constitute a quorum at the meeting of the shareholders and a majority of all the votes cast at any meeting of the shareholders shall be decisive of any action.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 3. Notice of the Meeting.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>Notice stating the place, day and hour of the meeting and the purpose for which the meeting has been called shall be given to all shareholders. Written notice stating the place, day and hour of meeting shall be delivered not less than five business days prior to the date of meeting by mail to the shareholders. Notice shall be deemed delivered when deposited in the United States mail.</text>
      <text>
        <em>ARTICLE III. BOARD OF DIRECTORS</em>
      </text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 1. Powers.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The affairs of the corporation shall be managed by a Board of Directors.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 2. Number of Directors.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The number of directors of a corporation shall be not less than three. Each director shall hold office until (a) the next annual meeting of the shareholders and until his or her successor has been duly elected and qualified or (b) until his or her death or (c) until he or she shall resign or shall have been removed from office by affirmative vote of the majority of the outstanding shareholders. A director may resign at any time by filing his or her written resignation with the secretary of the corporation.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 3. Meetings.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The annual meeting of the Board of Directors shall be held without any notice other than these bylaws immediately after and at the same place as the annual meeting of the shareholders or immediately after any adjourned session thereof.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 4. Special Meetings.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>Special meetings of the Board of Directors may be called at the request of the President or any two directors. Notice of the special meeting shall be given to all directors of the corporation personally.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 5. Quorum.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The majority of the number of directors in section 2 shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business at any meeting of the Board of Directors. The act of the majority of the directors present at the meeting at which a quorum is present shall be the act of the Board of Directors.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 6. Vacancies.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>Any vacancies occurring on the Board of Directors shall be filled by affirmative vote of the remaining directors then in office, though less than a quorum of the Board of Directors.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 7. Compensation.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Board of Directors may establish reasonable compensation for all directors for services rendered to the corporation as directors.</text>
      <text>
        <em>ARTICLE IV. OFFICERS</em>
      </text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 1. Number.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Board of Directors shall elect a President, Secretary, and a Treasurer, and such officers and agents as they may so desire. Any two offices may be held by the same person.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 2. Election.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The officers of the corporation shall be elected by the Board of Directors and shall be elected annually by the Board of Directors at the first meeting of the Board of Directors held after the annual meeting of the shareholders or any adjournment thereof.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 3. Removal and Vacancies.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>Any officer appointed by the Board of Directors may be removed by the Board of Directors with or without cause. A vacancy in any of the principal offices because of death, resignation, removal or disqualification or otherwise shall be filled by the Board of Directors for the unexpired portion of the term.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 4. President.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The President shall be the principal executive officer of the corporation and shall supervise and control all of the business affairs of the corporation subject to the direction and control of the Board of Directors.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 5. Secretary.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Secretary shall:</text>
      <text>(a) Keep all minutes of the shareholders' meetings and of meetings of the Board of Directors;</text>
      <text>(b) See that all notices are duly given in accordance with the provisions set forth in these bylaws;</text>
      <text>(c) Be custodian of the corporate records; and</text>
      <text>(d) In general, perform all duties incident to the office of secretary and have such other duties and exercise such authority as from time to time may be delegated or assigned by the President or by the Board of Directors.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 6. Treasurer.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Treasurer shall be the chief financial officer of the corporation and shall exercise general supervision over the receipt, custody, and disbursement of corporate funds.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Section 7. Salaries.</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The salaries of the principal officers shall be fixed from time to time by the Board of Directors. The salaries so fixed must be reasonable in relation to the services rendered.</text>
      <text>
        <em>ARTICLE V. AMENDMENTS</em>
      </text>
      <text>These bylaws may be altered, amended or repealed and new bylaws may be adopted by the shareholders at any annual or special meeting of the shareholders.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.060 was formerly codified as 29.0306</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.070</num>
      <heading>Dissolution</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A corporation formed pursuant to <cite path="29.03">this chapter</cite> may be dissolved whenever a resolution is adopted by at least two-thirds of the shareholders requesting dissolution and a certified copy of the resolution is filed with the Tribal Secretary of the Tribe. The resolution may designate a trustee or trustees to conduct the winding up of the corporation's affairs. The trustee or trustees appointed shall, as speedily as practicable after appointment, proceed to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Collect all sums due or owing to the corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Sell and convert to  cash all corporate assets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Pay all debts and liabilities of the corporation</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any property remaining after discharging the debts and liabilities of the corporation shall be distributed by the trustee or trustees to the shareholders.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.070 was formerly codified as 29.0307</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>29.03.080</num>
      <heading>Involuntary Dissolution</heading>
      <text>A private corporation may be involuntarily dissolved for failing to make its annual filing within 60 days of the deadline.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="Turtle Mountain Band of Chippewa Indians Res. No. 391-08-15"/>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§29.03.080 was formerly codified as 29.0308</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
